Finding aid to the Lamont-Corliss Family papers SSC.MS.00089
Sophia Smith Collection
Lamont-Corliss Family papers
1883-1975
Sophia Smith Collection
Lamont family
SSC.MS.00089
25 boxes (10 linear feet)
Philanthropist; Pacifist; Poet; and Philosopher. Papers document Florence Haskell Corliss and Thomas Lamont's family, social life, and philanthropic work. Topics include philosophy, philanthropy, Smith College, literature, socialism, United Nations. Materials include correspondence, writings (manuscripts), childhood writings, speeches, diaries, genealogical material, photographs, memorabilia, and clippings.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections. Collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be somewhat difficult to use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was gifted by Florence Haskell Corliss between 1965 and 2010. The accession numbers not listed in this finding aid are "no accession number" (1965-1990), 90S-6, and 91S-91.
Biographical / Historical
Florence Haskell Corliss was born Englewood, NJ in 1873. She graduated from Smith College in 1893, and received an M.A. in Philosophy from Columbia University. She married Thomas W. Lamont, banker and CEO of J.P. Morgan and Co. in 1895 and they had 4 children. She was interested in philanthropic activities, especially those related to education and international affairs/peace. She served as a Smith College trustee from 1911-25. She also supported the New School for Social Research and, in 1948, donated 150 acres in Palisades, NY to Columbia University for the establishment of The Center for Geography Studies. Lamont was a supporter of the League of Nations and the United Nations. She served on the board for League of Nations Association and the Executive Committee of the American Asssociation for the United Nations until her death in 1952. She also served on various committees of foreign policy associations and was active in NY literary circles. Her friends included Robert Frost, John Masefield, and H.G. Wells. In addition to her philanthropic work Lamont wrote and published stories, poetry and articles, and contributed to the Journal of Philosophy. She also travelled frequently in Europe, Asia, Mexico.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Scope and Contents
The Lamont-Corliss Family Papers extensive files of Florence and Thomas Lamont's social, family, and philanthropic correspondence, writings (manuscripts), speeches, photographs, memorabilia, and clippings. There is also material related to Florence Lamont's interest in and concern for international peace, philosophy, and poetry. Family material consists of childhood writings, diaries, correspondence, letters to mother, husband, children, employees, relative to family news, trips abroad, domestic items, address books, guest lists, passports, photographs, genealogical material, privately-printed family history, obituaries, letters of condolence, tributes. A considerable amount of Smith College (1889- 1894) includes correspondence with family and friends, lecture notes, notebooks, invitations, programs, valentines, photographs. Philanthropic papers consist of correspondence about contributions, especially with Smith College, associations for poetry and philosophy, organizations for international understanding, and charities in New York, New Jersey, and Florida. Philosophic and literary papers include correspondence with literary figures, published and unpublished manuscripts and speeches on world peace, poetry, and philosophy. There are a small number of photographs, mostly of family. Correspondents of note include Thomas William Lamont, 1870-1948; John Masefield, 1878-1967; Jan Christiaan Smuts, 1870-1950 (photocophies); Arnold Toynbee, Lamont family; and Corliss Lamont, 1916- 1965. Topics include philosophy, philanthropy, Smith College, literature, socialism, United Nations.
Authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; China--Description and travel--Sources; Europe--Description and travel--Sources; Japan--description and travel--Sources; Mexico--Description and travel--Sources; United States--Intellectual life--20th century--Sources; Peace movements--History--20th century--Sources; Philanthropists--United States--History--Sources; Poets, American--19th century--Biography--Sources; Women and peace--History--20th century--Sources; Women philosophers--United States--Biography--Sources; World War, 1914-1918--Protest movements--Sources; Lamont, Florence Haskell Corliss, 1873-1952; Lamont, Thomas, 1870-1916; Lamont, Corliss, 1902-; Corliss family; Genealogies; Writings; diaries; Speeches; correspondence; Brochures; Pamphlets; photographs; memorabilia; Books; Phonograph records; scrapbooks; clippings; Yearbooks; Notes; Lamont family; Lamont, Corliss, 1902- --Correspondence; Lamont, Thomas, 1870-1916--Correspondence; Masefield, John, 1878-1967--Correspondence; Smuts, Jan Christiaan, 1870-1950--Correspondence; Toynbee, Arnold, 1852-1883--Correspondence; American Association for the United Nations--History--Sources; League of Nations; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Cunningham, Priscilla; Lamont, Corliss and Thomas W. Austin; Lamont-Corliss family; Corliss family; Lamont, Florence Haskell Corliss, 1873-1952
- Florence Haskell Corliss Lamont correspondence, 1883-1951; 2002-S-0008; Cunningham, Priscilla; 0.5 linear feet
  Cunningham, Priscilla
  - Letters from"an Italian beau," from poet Robert Nichols, Rose Scheiderman, Ellizabeth Cutter Mortow and others, 1893-1951; 2002-S-0008 (Box 1)
- Materials related to Priscilla Cunningham, Eleanor Lamont Cunningham and Charles Cunningham, Corliss Lamont, 1932-2003; 2003-S-0040; Cunningham, Priscilla; 0.5 linear feet (1 box)
  - Correspondence: Corliss Lamont to Priscilla Cunningham, 1958-1977; 2003-S-0040 (Box 1)
  - Condolences regarding death of Eleanor Lamont Cunningham, 1961 May; 2003-S-0040 (Box 1)
  - Joyce Greenfell to Cunningham Family, 1963-1979; 2003-S-0040 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Eleanor Lamont Cunningham to Florence Corliss Lamont, 1949; 2003-S-0040 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Russell Banks, Joan Fontaine, Marilyn Horne, Douglas Dillon, Isaac Stern, Jacques-Yves Cousteau, Barbara Bush, 1986-2003; 2003-S-0040 (Box 1)
  - Marriage of Eleanor Lamont-Charles Cunningham: clippings, photographs, 1932; 2003-S-0040 (Box 1)
  - Photograph: Eleanor Lamont Cunningham and Priscilla Cunningham, circa 1938; 2003-S-0040 (Box 1)
  - Smith College notes, essays: Eleanor Lamont Cunningham, No date; 2003-S-0040 (Box 1)
  - Smith College Yearbook: Eleanor Lamont Cunningham, 1932; 2003-S-0040 (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Priscilla Cunningham and miscellaneous materials, 1931-1994; 2003-S-0074; Cunningham, Priscilla; 0.25 linear feet
  - Esther Lowell Burnett Cunningham correspondence, 1954-1956; 2003-S-0074 (Box 1)
  - Book: "Three Houses: A Narrative, 1955; 2003-S-0074 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, correspondence related to Thomas C. Mendenhall, 1958; 2003-S-0074 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Priscilla Cunningham and Elinor Gregory, 1957-1958; 2003-S-0074 (Box 1)
  - Photograph: Eleanor Lamont, 1931; 2003-S-0074 (Box 1)
  - Sarah Peck Meyer correspondence, resume, 1969-1994; 2003-S-0074 (Box 1)
- Priscilla Cunningham diaries and Smith College materials, 1946-1956; 2005-S-0020; Cunningham, Priscilla; 0.5 linear feet (1 box)
  - Smith College exams and notes, 1955-1956; 2005-S-0020 (Box 1)
- Priscilla Cunningham: photographs and correspondence, 1916-1972; 2006-S-0051; Cunningham, Priscilla; 0.5 linear feet
  - Childhood photographs, No date; 2006-S-0051 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from family members, 1918-1972; 2006-S-0051 (Box 1)
- Materials related to Paul Roche, Eleanor Allen Lamont Cunningham and Priscilla Cunningham, 1915-2007; 2008-S-0071; Cunningham, Priscilla; 1 linear feet (1 box)
  - Paul Roche correspondence, poems and related materials, 1964-2007; 2008-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Eleanor Allen Lamont Cunningham photo album, circa 1915; 2008-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Priscilla Cunningham correspondence and miscellaneous materials, 1983-2006; 2008-S-0071 (Box 1)
- Materials related to Florence Haskell Corliss Lamont, Thomas W. Lamont and Smith College, 1892-1971; 2009-S-0069; Cunningham, Priscilla; 0.25 linear feet (1 box)
  - Photographs of Florence Haskell Corliss Lamont, 1971, undated; 2009-S-0069 (Box 1)
  - Photograph of Thomas W. Lamont, undated; 2009-S-0069 (Box 1)
  - Smith College scrapbook, circa 1893; 2009-S-0069 (Box 1)
  - Smith College sketchbook, circa 1892-1893; 2009-S-0069 (Box 1)
- Smith College art notebooks of Priscilla Cunningham, 1956-1969; 2010-S-0076; Cunningham, Priscilla; 0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Priscilla Cunningham Smith College history of art notebooks, 1956-1969; 2010-S-0076 (Box 1)
    General
    Smith College Study SAbroad courses taught by Professor Clarence Kennedy and taken by Priscilla Cunningham
  - Priscilla Cunningham, Smith College history of art notebooks, 1956-1969; 2010-S-0076 (Box 2)